David Backman Collection of Photographs 1953-1989 PR 383
New-York Historical Society
David Backman collection of photographs
1953-1989, undated
New-York Historical Society
Backman, David
PR 383
.5 Linear feet in 1 box
This collection, assembled and donated by David Backman, contains 10 portraits of Marilyn Monroe by André de Dienes, and 21 photographs by photojournalist Ken Regan.
Scope and Contents
This collection, assembled and donated by David Backman, contains 10 portraits of Marilyn Monroe by André de Dienes, and 21 photographs by photojournalist Ken Regan.
Conditions Governing Access
Available by advance appointment only.
To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Biographical / Historical
Ken Regan (d. 2012) worked for over five decades documenting pop culture, sports, foreign conflicts, and other current events. Credited with over 200 magazine covers, Regan was most well-known for a discretion and professionalism which earned him intimate shooting access to famous politicians, musicians, and other celebrities.
Regan also covered major events for magazines such as Time, Sports Illustrated, Life, and Newsweek. In the 1970s he founded Camera 5, an agency of 15 photographers who covered wars, riots and demonstrations, and other national and international hard news and human interest stories.
André de Dienes (1913-1985) was a Hungarian American fashion photographer best known for his early portraits of the actress Marilyn Monroe.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into two series; Series I consists of photographs by Ken Regan, and Series II contains photographs by André de Dienes. The photographs are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of David Backman, 2013 and 2015.
Separated Materials
This material was originally included in the finding aid for the Michael Sonnenfeldt Collection of Theatre, Film, and Entertainment Photography PR 305, which was processed by project intern Brynn White in 2014. This material was separated into a discrete collection and finding aid in 2019 by processing archivist Marybeth Kavanagh.
Celebrities -- United States -- Portraits; Photographs; Regan, Ken; De Dienes, André, 1913-1985; Monroe, Marilyn, 1926-1962
- Series I: Photographs by Ken Regan
  Scope and Contents
  This series, donated and assembled by David Backman, contains Ken Regan of musical figures Keith Richards and Bill Graham, Regan's mentor; politicians Ted Kennedy, John Lindsay, and Ronald Reagan; athletes Jackie Joyner, Oscar Gamble, and Gary Player in addition to the 1962 New York Mets baseball team; and news and entertainment personalities Al Weston, Tab Hunter, and Dr. Delano Merriweather.
  - Ford, Betty, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Gamble, Oscar, undated; 61895 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Baseball player
  - Graham, Bill, 1974, undated; 61889 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Concert promoter. Two images, one with Jim Morrison and Ray Manzarek of the Doors; one of Graham getting a pie in the face.
  - Hunter, Tab and Zimbalist, Stephanie, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Joyner, Jackie, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    also know as Jackie Joyner-Kersee. Photo with the staff of a McDonald's restaurant.
  - Kennedy, Ted, 1974, undated; 61890 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Two images: one ice skating with Ethel Kennedy at Rockefeller Center; one with Jean Kennedy Smith at an Ali-Frazier boxing match
  - Lindsay, John, undated; 61891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Two images.
  - Merriweather, Delano, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Physician and former track and field athlete.
  - New York Mets, 1962; 61896 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Two images of players on field during a game.
  - Player, Gary, 1971; 61894 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Golfer.
  - Reagan, Ronald, 1985; 61892 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    with Nancy Reagan, Jackie Kennedy Onassis, and John F. Kennedy Jr.
  - Richards, Keith, 1977, 1989; 61893 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Weston, Av, 1982-1983; 61897 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Journalist, ABC News executive; 3 images, including one with Barbara Walters.
  - Wyman, Bill, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Photographs by Andre de Dienes
  - Marilyn Monroe, 1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    10 portraits.